<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:distill="https://distill.pub/journal/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Cody R. Tuttle</title>
    <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app</link>
    <atom:link href="https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>Cody R. Tuttle
</description>
    <generator>Distill</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on poverty</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-09-13-thoughts-on-poverty</link>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Hey folks - I don’t have much time to post right now, but in the
spirit of posting more frequently and being less of a perfectionist, I’m
going to write for 15 minutes about my current musings and thoughts on
poverty. The new poverty numbers from the Census Bureau came out today,
and they’ve got me somewhere in between my head and my heart reflecting
on the dynamics of poverty - the intellectual and scholarly
understanding, the political economy and societal optics, the lived
reality and experience of people in poverty. With all of this, I’m just
going to take 15 minutes and just get my thoughts down in writing. Like
I alluded to, this is probably going to be something in between
intellectual/academic musings and personal/emotional reflection. But
whatever it ends up actually being, it’s the honest and raw thoughts
that are swirling in my brain right now. I hope to find the time soon to
do a little more digging into these reflections, both from a conceptual
and philosophical perspective, but also the data and research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here it goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will start out with an obvious but I think important qualification
on all of these thoughts: I am a very privileged white male living in an
upper-middle class neighborhood with a poverty rate of next to nothing.
I have never experienced real poverty aside from being a broke college
student. I didn’t experience poverty growing up as a kid, nor have I
experienced poverty as an adult. I live in a decently large city, so I
see poverty around me fairly frequently, but I am not residentially- or
socially-proximal to poverty in the way that I’m reflecting on now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new poverty numbers have me considering how complex and dynamic
poverty truly is. At a very top line, without actually reading into the
details just yet, the Census Bureau released the poverty statistics for
2021, and poverty by most conceptions is down considerably from 2020,
especially child poverty. This is a true dynamic, and it’s a good thing,
full stop. But the official poverty numbers, whether in the form of the
official poverty measure or the supplemental poverty measure, do not
even come close to really capturing the experience of people living in
financial and material deprivation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Official statistics, whether absolute (like the official poverty
measure) or relative (like the supplemental poverty measure) are based
on hard thresholds and cutoffs for who falls into the “poverty” category
and who does not, because they have to be. But what these cutoffs miss
is the experience of people who are just beyond that bright line -
people who have income a little higher than whatever threshold is being
used, but are actually no better off than the folks just below it. So
much policy, so many benefits, so much scholarship and research, is
based on these arbitrary lines, and it leaves out the real experience of
so many people. So many families are denied benefits because they have
income a few dollars higher than the poverty criteria being used,
benefits that the new numbers and years of evidence show actually help
families improve their circumstances and life prospects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing is that these numbers, especially the official poverty
measure, are based on calculations taken at one point during the year.
They’re a sampling of folks who were above and below the cutoff at one
point during the year. But this completely missed the inherent dynamic
nature of poverty. Lots of research shows that it’s just really really
easy to fall into poverty. Most families and individuals are just one
emergency or accident away from slipping into devastating financial
circumstances that could completely redefine their entire life
trajectory. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;My&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; family is just one emergency
away from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet. Something that the new numbers also miss is that communities
of color and other historically and currently marginalized groups are
&lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much more likely to experience poverty than white folks. The
truth is that my family and I are most likely able to weather an
emergency or shock a lot more easily than another family that looks just
like us but are Black, simply because of the societal and generational
privilege we are privy to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poverty is complex and dynamic. There are so many ways of knowing
that we need to tap into - not just the official (or supplemental)
statistics, but deeper quantitative analysis that looks at distributions
and timing, and most importantly, real qualitative lived experience of
folks in and near poverty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="r distill-force-highlighting-css"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <distill:md5>c1417144e3ca13ac96d48d64739aefc5</distill:md5>
      <category>no code</category>
      <category>poverty</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-09-13-thoughts-on-poverty</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NYT bestsellers</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-08-10-nyt-bestsellers</link>
      <description>An exploration of NYT bestselling authors using {reactable}.</description>
      <category>R</category>
      <category>reactable</category>
      <category>reading</category>
      <category>books</category>
      <category>NYT</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-08-10-nyt-bestsellers</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quick updates and musings</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-08-06-quick-updates-and-musings</link>
      <description>A brief note about where I've been and where I might be going.</description>
      <category>no code</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-08-06-quick-updates-and-musings</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Major Marathon Winners</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-02-07-analysis-of-major-marathon-winners</link>
      <description>A brief foray into winners of world major marathons, 1970-2018.</description>
      <category>R</category>
      <category>running</category>
      <category>marathons</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-02-07-analysis-of-major-marathon-winners</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2022-02-07-analysis-of-major-marathon-winners/analysis-of-major-marathon-winners_files/figure-html5/time-across-years-men-1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" width="1248" height="768"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on the 2020 poverty statistics release</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-09-15-notes-on-the-2020-poverty-statistics-release</link>
      <description>Poverty is down from 2019 to 2020 (by the SPM) - musings on the newest batch of data on poverty and income from the Census Bureau</description>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-09-15-notes-on-the-2020-poverty-statistics-release</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Test Run with VS Code</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-08-02-test-run-with-vs-code</link>
      <description>A short description of the post.</description>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-08-02-test-run-with-vs-code</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-08-02-test-run-with-vs-code/test-run-with-vs-code_files/figure-html5/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" width="1248" height="768"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plug for the Correlates of State Policy Shiny App</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-04-12-plug-for-the-correlates-of-state-policy-shiny-app</link>
      <description>A quick shout out to a really cool and valuable tool for social scientists</description>
      <category>state policy</category>
      <category>no code</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-04-12-plug-for-the-correlates-of-state-policy-shiny-app</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Shiny App on World Coffee Ratings!</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-04-05-new-shiny-app-on-world-coffee-ratings</link>
      <description>Short plug for my new Shiny app on world coffee ratings</description>
      <category>shiny</category>
      <category>R</category>
      <category>coffee</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2021-04-05-new-shiny-app-on-world-coffee-ratings</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing my 2020 running performance</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-13-analyzing-my-running-performance-using-strava-data</link>
      <description>Exploring my year in running using data from the Strava app</description>
      <category>R</category>
      <category>running</category>
      <category>strava</category>
      <category>leaflet</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-13-analyzing-my-running-performance-using-strava-data</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-13-analyzing-my-running-performance-using-strava-data/analyzing-my-running-performance-using-strava-data_files/figure-html5/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" width="1248" height="768"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A true welcome</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-07-a-true-welcome</link>
      <description>Why I'm here</description>
      <category>no code</category>
      <category>intro</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-07-a-true-welcome</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CFPB Analysis</title>
      <dc:creator>Cody Tuttle</dc:creator>
      <link>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-02-cfpb-analysis</link>
      <description>A repurposing of a post I did on my old blog site last January. Wanted to get some content up here to see how the workflow goes.</description>
      <category>R</category>
      <category>CFBP</category>
      <category>equity</category>
      <category>banking</category>
      <guid>https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-02-cfpb-analysis</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://codyrtuttle.netlify.app/posts/2020-12-02-cfpb-analysis/cfpb-analysis_files/figure-html5/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" width="1248" height="768"/>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
